Im in a "project" directory and we have an "index.html" file.
lets put the editor and the terminal on the left, and while I work on a project you'll see how the repository is going to change
So, first, I will, of course create a repository with "git init" and add "index.html" to it.
right after the first commit is made git will create a default branch which is called "master"
from technical perspective branch is a special link to a commit, where you can even see it if you open ".git" directory
and see "refs" -> "heads", here, its a "master" branch
literally this small file and now it referrs to a commit with this identifier
this is a full identifier of our first commit. Its 40 digits long
and if we look at the output of the commit command we can see the first digits of this identifier
this way of checking the branches, by checking the ".git" directory is unconventional
because its not very reliable, as branches are in this directory only at the very beginning
and git is packing its data after a while by turning it into a special format and putting in another place
So you might not find it here and to check for available branches one should use the "git branch" command
or "git branch -v", to see the branch and the commit information its pointing to
The identifier here is abbreviated, but git allows us to use both full and abbreviated
identifiers, but the shorter ones should consist of 4 or more first digits,
so that git could uniquely identify the commit
so that at right I have these abbreviated identifiers
There is one more important file in the ".git" directory that is called "head".
"head" is used by git repository to understand what branch are we at now
as we can switch between the branches and "head" is actually pointing to the current branch. Now we are in the "master" branch.
Technically "head" could point to a commit, but its a special case and an extremely rare one, we'll have a look at it later
Most of the time its a branch, like here
now lets close
the ".git" directory. I'll go back to it from time to time so we could better understand how things are working behind the scenes
but you wont need it in your day-to-day job.
Lets continue with our development, make a new file, like "script.js" and add a small function here
add new script to "index.html" and
add our changes to the repository
now have a look at the right side of the screen
when commit is done, git checks where is "head" pointing to. "head" points to "master"
and "master" contains the identifier of our first commit
this way git figures our where are we now and
parent info is written to the new commit. In other words parent is the one we used to create our commit, which is a child one
this one
right after our new commit is created
link to the master is switched to it, so literally new identifier is written to master.
Commit to which the branch is pointing called a "HEAD", so in this case our last commit is the HEAD of the master branch.
If we print the list of branches with "-v" we can see that the "HEAD" is updated
Lets make another change and create a "sayBye" function to complement "sayHi" function.
давайте сделаем еще изменения в дополнение к функции "sayHi" создадим функцию "sayBye"
Now if I make a new commit exactly the same thing will happen
have a look at it here, on the right, we have a new commit and link to the master is moved to it
We could keep committing it further, but imagine we have a new idea
which implementation requires to create a new branch, that we will do using "git branch" comand
and this time we give it a name of the new branch, lets call it a "feature".
Branch is ready, if we have a look at our ".git" directory we can see it
here it is
new branch is now pointing to the same commit as master, see, so that new branch creation is a really fast thing to do for git
just a new link to commit is created
our next step is to switch to new branch
for that we need to update the "head". Now its like that. To switch we have to use "git checkout"
and the name of the branch after that
Here we go, perfect. As you see the "head" link was changed, now we are on a new branch and lets make some work here
Lets close the ".git" directory
and make a new function in a "script.js" file and call it something like "work"
add it to the repository
have a look at the image on the right, new commit was created
as current branch or the one to which head points to is "feature" the pointer was moved to "feature"
new commit identifier was added to "feature" while master branch remained the same
Lets check the current state of the branches wth "git branch -v" and
we see that we have 2 branches and the "*" symbol is pointing to the current one and the current one points to the new commit
Lets make something else, like call our new function in the "index.html".
Saving the changes and
we have another commit of the "feature" branch
Of course I want to stress it once again
that technically the branch is only a link to a single commit, but
we say that commits belong to the branch or are inside the branch of all commits that are having its parents listed in the chain of parents
As you can see, right now all the commits are in the "feature" branch
The sense of it is very simple. All of these contain changes that led to the current state of the "feature" branch.
And first 3 commits also belong to the "master" branch and form the state of the project in the "master" branch
Lets continue the development. We can work on the "feature" branch further, but its quite possible that till we are done with it
we'll have to go back to the "master" branch to add some changes there. We use "git checkout" command to switch the branch
in this case we are in a "feature" and "git checkout master" will do 2 things:
first - it will change the link to the current in the "head" and second -
will move the files from the master branch to the project directory in the state we left them
while we made our previous commit, to which master is pointing
You see, the "head" moved and the file in the editor got changed. Now we have
the "index.html" and "script.js" from the master branch in the working directory. We can go back from the "master" branch
If we change our mind, and again we can see in the editor, that files were restored from the "feature" branch. Its quite straight forward as you can see,
using the "git checkout" we can switch between
the work in the "feature" branch and the main master branch as changes done to "feature" are fading away on checkout.
And of course in the master we can go on with development and the changes there are going to fade away if we switch back to "feature".
So as these are only the references to commit they play a role of the isolated flows of development
Lets move further and Im in the "master" branch again and Im going to make some changes here
ну что ж пойдем дальше сейчас я снова на ветке мастер и собираюсь внести кое-какие исправления
while they are not ready Im going to isolate them from the main development flow, extracting to their own branch and call it a "fix"
the "-b" in the "checkout" command means that we have to create a new branch and switch to it immediately
so its same as if I ran 2 commands: "git branch fix" and "git checkout fix" then.
Lets run, so, we've made a new branch, which is a commit pointer named "fix" and
checkout switched the "head" to it, while both "fix" and "master" are pointing at the same commit right now. Lets even have a look
"git branch -v" see, their files are the same and now, while at "fix" Im making my changes
previously, when I made a "script.js" I made the functions but forgot to call them
so lets add the "sayHi()" call to the "index.html"
Looks great!
Saving the changes in the repository
and now I've decided to call "sayBye()" as well
one more commit
Lets note that new commits were moving the "fix" pointer as "head" is pointing to it now.